LeRoy "Damu" Smith 116 116
Stage
LeRoy "Damu" Smith Papers
1990-1994
Stage
116
2.5 linear feet; 1 box
LeRoy "Damu" Smith was a social justice activist who worked for environmental justice and anti-racism, among other causes. Among the records are biographical material, notes, photographs, audiocassette tapes, and research files. The research files cover Angola, South Africa, Korea, Iraq, the environment, and organizations such as the French Street Umoja Connection, Louisiana Cancer Alley, and the National Alliance Against Racist and Political Repression.
Custodial History
Gift of Lynn Moore, 2006.
Biographical / Historical
LeRoy Wesley Smith was born on December 6, 1951 to Sylvester and Vernice Smith in St Louis, Missouri. Throughout his high school years, Smith participated in a program called the Sophia House, a project dedicated to developing leadership skills in young black men. Administered by Jesuit priest, Smith learned about civil rights struggles through the program. When Smith was 17 years old, he attended a black solidarity rally hosted by the Black United Fund in Cairo, Illinois. At the rally, Smith listened to speeches given by Rev. Jessie Jackson, poet and activist Amiri Baraka, singer Nina Simone and the Rev. Ralph Abernathy, then an advisor to Martin Luther King, Jr. Smith became involved in civil rights justice at home and within the African diaspora. Smith graduated from Vashon High School in 1970 and entered St. John's University in Collegeville, Minnesota. It was here that he started to become more organized in his activism, as head of the Organization of African American Students, Smith and the students sought changes on campus. He and his fellow students took over the administration building and demanded changes to the climate of hostility for black students on campus. During his college days, Smith changed his name to Damu Amiri Imara, a Swahili name, means blood, strength and leadership. Smith moved to D.C. in 1974, and became active in community organizations. Smith was one of the first black activists to target environmental racism as a problem that needed to be addressed. Smith worked with a number of organizations including the National Alliance against Racial and Political Violence, the American Friends Service Committee, Greenpeace USA, National Black Independent Political Party, National Black Environmental Justice Network, and Black Voices for Peace for which he was the founder and co-chair. Smith passed away on May 5, 2006.
Scope and Contents
The LeRoy "Damu" Smith papers document Smiths' involvement in activism and community organizations. Among the records are biographical material, notes, photographs, audiocassette tapes, and research files. The research files cover Angola, South Africa, Korea, Iraq, the environment, and organizations such as the French Street Umoja Connection, Louisiana Cancer Alley, and the National Alliance Against Racist and Political Repression.
- Series 1
  - Africa Miscellaneous, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Africa Miscellaneous, 1987-1993 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Africa Miscellaneous, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Africa Miscellaneous, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Africa Food Crisis, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Africa - Southern Africa Summer Project, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Africa - Angola, 1985-1990 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Africa Angola, 1986-1990 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Africa - Angola, 1990 1990 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Africa - Angola, 1990 1990 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Africa Angola, 1990 1990 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Africa Angola, 1991 1991 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Africa - Angola, 1988 - 1990 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Africa Angola (No date), undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Damu Smith Photos, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Damu Smith Collection, 2004-2006 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Black Americas Stake in the Struggle for Disarmament and Peace, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - The US Attacks on Angola, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Damu's Notes and Statements, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - National Rainbow Coalition and Million Man March, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Towards a Southern Strategy for Green Peace, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Louisiana, 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Arusha Tanzania, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Environmental Justice Pamphlet, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - African American Church Leaders Envionrmental Justice/Racism Fact Finding Mission, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Southern Louisiana Aids Coaltion Week Long Capacity Building Training, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - National Enviornmental Justice Advisory Council ( 1 of 2), 2002 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - National Enviornmental Justice Advisory Council ( 2 of 2), 2002 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Environment, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Environment, 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Environment, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Environment, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - SOC Leadership Conference, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Environment, 1991-1994 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Environment Greenpeace, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Environment Greenpeace, 1999-2001 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Environment Greenpeace, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Environment Greenpeace, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Environment Greenpeace, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Environment Greenpeace, 1997-2001 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Greenpeace, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Essence Magazine Letter, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Environment Greenpeace, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Calls for Support, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Environment Greenpeace, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Greenpeace, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Environment NBEJN, 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Environment NBEJN, 2002-2003 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Environment NBEJN, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Louisiana Cancer Alley, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Louisiana Cancer Alley, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Louisiana Cancer Alley, 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Louisiana Cancer Alley, 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Louisiana Cancer Alley, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Louisiana Cancer Alley, 1998-200 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Louisiana Cancer Alley, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Louisiana Cancer Alley, 1930-1998 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Louisiana Cancer Alley, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Louisiana Cancer Alley, 1990-1998 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Louisiana Cancer Alley, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Louisiana Cancer Alley, 2000-2002 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Louisiana Cancer Alley, 1995-1998 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Louisiana Cancer Alley, 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Louisiana Hurricanes, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Louisiana Hurricanes, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Middle East, 1983-2002 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Middle East, 1991-2005 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Other, 1992-1995 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Other, 1983-2005 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Other Clippings, 1985-1994 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Other- Notes/Notebooks, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Other- Notes/Notebooks, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Other- Clippings, 1992-2006 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Other- Notes/Notebooks, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Other- Notes/Notebooks, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Other - Notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Other - Notes, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Other - Notes, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Other - Notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Other - Notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Other - Notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Other - Notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Other - Notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Peace, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Peace, 1982-2002 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Peace, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Peace, 2002-2003 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Peace, 2002-2005 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Prisons, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Peace, 1995-2003 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Peace, 1992-2005 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Other Letters (1:2), 1983-2002 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Other Letters (2:2), 1983-2002 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Other Letters, 1989-2003 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Other Letters, 1984-2002 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Other Letters, 1992-2005 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Email to Damu, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Other Clippings, 1998-2002 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Other Bios, 1983-2006 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Damu Articles, 1983-1987 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Other Bios, 1977-2005 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Other Bios, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Other Bios, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Other Bios, Undated (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Awards Circa, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - "Spirit in Action", 2002 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Recommendations, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Notes, 1992-2005 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Speaking Engagements, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Letter Head, Undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Haiti, 1991-1995 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Health, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Health, 2004 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Health, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Health, 1992-2004 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Housing, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Housing, 1985-2005 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Human Rights, 1985-2005 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Human Rights, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Louisiana Cancer Alley, 1970-1995 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Louisiana, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Louisiana, 1992-2004 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Louisiana - Cancer Alley, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Louisiana - Cancer Alley, 1992-2001 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Louisiana - Cancer Alley, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Korea, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Korea, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Korea, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Korea, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Korea, 1989-1992 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Korea, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Iraq, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Iraq, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Iraq, 1991-2001 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Iraq, 1991-2003 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Korea, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Photograph, undated (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Environmental Justice Workshop, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Environment, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Environment, 1993-1997 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Environment, 1992-1993 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Environment, 1995-2000 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Organization Correspondence, 1994-1995 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Organization Correspondence, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Legal Paperwork, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - National Black Environment, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Environmental Justice Workshop, 2003 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Environment, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Environment Articles, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1994-1995 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Environment, 1995-2000 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Memorandums, 1994-1995 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Environment Articles, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - "Sustainable America", 1996 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Other Notes, Undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Other Notes, Undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Other Notes, Undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Other Notes, Undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Other Notes, Undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Other Notes, Undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Other Notes, Undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Other Notes, Undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Other Notes, Undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Other Notes, Undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Other Notes, Undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Miscellanous, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Africa- other, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Million Man March Commemorative Anthology, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Campaign to Stop Government Spying, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - National African American Network Against Gulf Intervention African American Conference Invite, 1991 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - National Alliance Against Racist and Political Repression, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - National Black Enviornmental Justice Network Speaking Invitation, 2004 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Meeting Overview, 1979 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Organizations Inc. Awards Celebration, 2005 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Organization of African American Students Correspondence, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Rainbow Coalition Membership Renewal, 1994 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Clippings, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - United Methodist Seminiars on National and International Affairs "Racism in the U.S Program Schedule, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Historical Magazines/Journals, 1980-2001 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - US News and Time Magazines, 2005 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Africacare Day, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Stand for Truth - Notes, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Africa Articles, undated (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Memo re. African American Objectors to Gulf Crisis, 1991 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - National Black Enviornmental Justice Network Correspondence, 2003 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Reference Desk/ Pan African Student Union, undated (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Africa - South Africa (Anti Apartheid), 2004 (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Subseries: Event /Program, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Family/ Personal Lits of Relatives, 1979 (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Civil Rights/Liberties, 2006 (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - ANC Office Procedures, undated (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - Community: Advisory Neighborhood Commission ANC Manual, 1991 (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - EPA Grants Program Pre Application Kit, 1994 (Box 10, Folder 28)
  - National Black Caucus State Leg. Briefing, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 29)
  - Community ANC Meeting Flyer, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 30)
  - Public Health Statement on Mercury, undated (Box 10, Folder 31)
  - List of ANC Commissioners, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 32)
  - Damu Smith Ballot Profile, undated (Box 10, Folder 33)
  - Community: Advisory Neighborhood Commission Damu Smith Flyer, undated (Box 10, Folder 34)
  - Community: Advisory Neighborhood Commission ANC Stationary, undated (Box 10, Folder 35)
  - Greenpeace: Incoming Correspondence, 2000 (Box 10, Folder 36)
  - Textual Drafts, undated (Box 10, Folder 37)
  - Africa: Sub-Series: Reports, 2003 (Box 10, Folder 38)
  - Greenpeace Events, 2000 (Box 10, Folder 39)
  - Clippings, 2002 (Box 10, Folder 40)
  - Medical Physical Exam, undated (Box 10, Folder 41)
  - Family Personal Thank you Card, undated (Box 10, Folder 42)
  - Notes on Housing Apartment Outreach Strategy, undated (Box 10, Folder 43)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 10, Folder 44)
  - Damu Smith Address, undated (Box 10, Folder 45)
  - Article re: DS Health, 2005 (Box 10, Folder 46)
  - Millions More Movement Conference, 2005 (Box 10, Folder 47)
  - National African American Network, undated (Box 10, Folder 48)
  - Subject Article Files, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 49)
  - Photos, undated (Box 10, Folder 50)
  - Notebook, undated (Box 10, Folder 51)
  - Handwritten Notes, undated (Box 10, Folder 52)
  - Environment, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Environment, undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Environment, 1996-2005 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Environment, 1992-1994 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Environment, 1994-1995 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Environment, 1994-1995 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Environment, 1994-1995 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Environment, 1996 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Damu's Writings, undated (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - State of the Race, 2004 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Photos, undated (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Photos, undated (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Photos, undated (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Photos, undated (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Photos, undated (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Assignment Photography Price Flyers, undated (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Daytime Planner, 2000 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - The Reporter's Enviornmental Handbook, 1995 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Africa (South Africa) ANC Journals, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Africa (South Africa) ANC Journals, 1994 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Africa (South Africa) ANC Constitution, undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Africa (South Africa) ANC Trip Travel Materials, 1994 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - PostCards, undated (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Africa (South Africa), 1978-1987 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Africa (South Africa), 1988-1990 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Africa (South Africa), 1990-1999 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Africa (South Africa), undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Africa (South Africa) Anti Apartheid, undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Southern Organizing Committee for Economic and Social Justice Racism Conference, 1992 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Southern Organizing Committee for Economic and Social Justice Programs, 1992-1994 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Southern Organizing Committee for Economic and Social Justice Correspondence, 1991-1994 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - National Alliance Against Racist and Political Repression Terrence Johnson Case, 1979 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - National Alliance Against Racist and Political Repression Washington 10 Clippings, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - National Alliance Against Racist and Political Repression Washington 10 Case Synopsis, undated (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - National Alliance Against Racist and Political Repression "What Has to Be Done: Theory and Practice of Mass Struggle, undated (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Black Voices for Peace Correspondence, 2003 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Black Voices for Peace Event Invitation, 2003 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Black Voices for Peace Programs, 2004-2006 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - BlcK Voices for Peace Aknowledgements, 2005 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Black Voices for Peace Event Program, 2005 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Awards Reception Invitations, 2005 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - French Street UMOJA Connection Correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - French Street UMOJA Connection Flyers, 1985-1991 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - French Street UMOJA Connection Organization Meetings, 1986-1987 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - French Street UMOJA Connection Press Releases, 1986 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - French Street UMOJA Connection Memorandums, 1987 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - French Street UMOJA Connection Mission Statement, undated (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - National African American Tobacco Prevention Network Website Printout, 2003 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - National African American Tobacco Prevention Network Draft Letter to Black Magazines, undated (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - National African American Tobacco Prevention Network Correspondence, 2003 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Damu Interview - Anti War Rally CSPAN etc. Video Tape, 2003-2004 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - NBC Toxic Avenger etc. Video Tape, 1994 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - James McHenry Elementary School Music Fest Highlights Video Tape, 2002-2006 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Nightlife Town Hall Meeting Video Tape, undated (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Tape for Whats Poisoning our Communities Video Tape, undated (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Damu Smith Weta Now w/ Bill Mowers Video Tape, 2002 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - unlabled Video Tape, undated (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Angola The Struggle Continues Video Tape, 1987 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Louisiana Enviornmental Action Network Homeer LA News Coverage Video Tape, undated (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Coming to the Light Jesus People Against Pollution, undated (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Cassettes and DVDs, undated (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Cassettes, undated (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Cassettes, undated (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Cassettes, undated (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Cassettes, undated (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Buttons, undated (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Posters and Movie Reels, undated (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Newspapers (Flatbox), undated (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Slides, undated (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Cassettes, undated (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Cassettes, undated (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Posters, undated (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Cassettes, undated (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Cassettes, undated (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - Cassettes, undated (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - Cassettes, undated (Box 32, Folder 1)